[Music]
ERS-1 was the first remote sensing
satellite for the environment that ESA
had flown there were meteorological
satellites before but ERS-1 was the
pioneer
measuring all types of different
environmental information but the first
in Europe ERS-1
[Music]
was the starting point for everything
that in
a lot of the observation capabilities
that we have in space now that we take
for granted after years one we had many
other missions so basically ERS-1 is
the
grandfather of all other missions
in july 1991
the European Space Agency launched a
unique earth observation satellite from
Europe's spaceport at Kourou
[Music]
and over the days after launch it's
called the launch and early operations
phase the satellite was stabilized the
instruments are switched on and then
they're checked out to see that they're
working correctly
and that's where the problem started we
were waiting for the first data to
arrive
and in particular the the data of the
radar imaging
in english Synthetic Aperture Radar SAR
so we were waiting for that because that
was really the
main instrument of ERS-1 so we were
waiting for
you know the first image this was from
from the start this was going to be
exciting thing
and i think it was on uh
saturday
if i'm not mistaken it may have been
july 27th or 29th and the
data was to be received
there were the primary station was
Kiruna
and Fucino which was a secondary station
was was listening in
[Music]
a big vip event was planned down in
Fucino station for the first SAR
acquisition i think they even took the
the minister of research down there but
to all the italian vips
so in real time the satellite downloaded
the data it was recorded onto
HDDT high density digital tape
and the tape was played back
into the sar processor and
in those days there was a CRT
monitor cathode ray monitor where the
image as it was being processed would
scroll up
and what scroll up was basically
unrecognizable gray streaky rubbish not
a SAR image at all
i i always describe it as
it's like when the old tv channels used
to stop broadcasting and you get snow
nothing there so that was
uh
unexpected the
the image resulting in that processing
was very blurred blurred at the point
that my colleagues like Mark Doherty and
Stephen Coulson were desperate that's where
the panic set in i kind of think the
minister kind of said
we just paid
500 million euros for this
and
there was a serious concern that the
satellite wasn't working correctly
there were also a lot of
anxiety in our management
here at ESRIN at headquarters because
ERS-1 one really was the first
satellite and we were not completely
sure that the problem was in the
processing it could have been a problem
really on board with with the instrument
meaning that we would have failed the
development of that our first
Earth observation satellite you don't know
whether it's really a problem
with the satellite i don't know shaking
is it the the the SAR instrument on board
where there is a
the radar antenna partially broken or
not completely open
is it something going wrong in the
transmission of the signal
so there are plenty of um
of reasons that it does not work
so the tape was shipped back to ESRIN
and that's where
um actually Mark and Henri who were
leading the investigation began work to
try and find out what the problem was
i was a bit of a
bystander in those days but i was
obviously had some previous SAR
experience and was was following the
investigation we got the data from
Fucino and by the way at that time
there was no internet so someone had to
carry on on the card
the tapes it's about 100 kilometers from
here and then we we got the tape where
we had the whole data and we processed as
well and
did not work
we had a complete replica here in ESRIN
of the fast delivery processing chain
which is installed in all of the
receiving stations
and
Henri quite correctly began a very
systematic methodical
check step by step
of what was going on whether the data
was being ingested properly into the sar
processor whether the star processor was
configured correctly but all of this was
taking a lot of time and each time he
did a check and a run the results were
the same this horrible gray streaky
rubbish
the same thing by the way was was in
progress at Kiruna station
with what was called the project team so
these are the guys who designed and
built the satellite
and they were
again systematically going through so
there was a bit of a race if you want uh
between the project team in ESTEC
and the um
shall we say the amateurs down in ESRIN
the guys who who haven't built a
satellite but were going to process the
data and work on the applications
they were at a disadvantage because they
didn't have a system that was really set
up to let them easily
understand what was going wrong we had a
thing called the verification mode SAR
processor here in ESRIN which was fully
configurable you could change all the
processing parameters it had bells and
whistles you could do all sorts of
things with it and they didn't have that
at Kiruna they had a machine there the
FDPC the fast delivery processing chain
built for speed
uh hardwired and less configurable we
ran it through the processor and
actually updated common image but it it
was a mess
and uh
but what i really visibly recall from
that one of my our colleagues Henri Laur
who was
the
he was specialized in SAR processing
and applications i remember vividly
seeing Henri standing in front of this
awfully
awful image and pointing out it's
Flevoland there's the transponders i
could see these things and we were
awesome the guys
and i remember i was looking at that
image and i knew where it was actually
that image was acquired
over the Netherlands the center of the
research the the polder called Flevoland
and i remember i was saying to to to
Mark look i can recognize it's very
blurred
but uh here we can see Amsterdam you see
Utrecht? and we see Flevoland
and mark
but that's not really and he was
absolutely right he could recognize it
so we were
Henri was was changing the parameters
and he was doing this
with the real genius of the story who
was Paul Lim
who was the engineer in Vancouver who
had designed and built the VMP which was
sitting here in ESRIN
so we were on the phone to Vancouver
it was quite late in the evening here
early in the morning in Vancouver and we
were telling Paul what the results were
of the changes that he'd made to the
processing with Paul
he was actually rebuilding the software
in Canada
recompiling it so that we could run it
in ESRIN and we were processing the data
and doing the analysis and what actually
happened
was
we did that first processing and then we
said let's change some of the processing
parameters precisely what they couldn't
easily do in Kiruna we just changed the
number and re-ran the processing
and you know what it happened
it made it worse
we up scrolled the image it wasn't the
image it was the blobs and they got
further apart
but that was wonderful because we could
go and and
with a ruler literally on the image
measure what should have been a point
and instead was a blur and say well it's
twice as blurred as it was before then
we talked to Paul
and he said well if that's made it worse
maybe this could be the source of the
problem
and
what he did was
based on those very rough estimates uh
figured out that if we
flipped
a plus to a minus basically in the
processing maybe it would make it
uh better suddenly at the idea but maybe
we should try that which is to invert
what we said the
I/Q channel of the signal
okay let's stop
with um the systematic stuff i've got a
wild idea i'm going to change something
and let's see what happens
so i did that
we reconfigured the code we re ran you
know at that time the image did not
appear immediately it was ...
and then we saw the image as it was
being processed coming scrolling up and
we were just it was a perfectly
beautiful focused SAR image and
suddenly the image was perfect you know
like a revelation
[Music]
so that was quite a moment and when that
happened
uh mark went into orbit um there was a
whole stream of uh
shall we say colourful language it was
joy and jubilation i i mean i
i don't think you remember
the moments of
what you
said or what you did i think we were
um
i mean we we felt it was
a sort of history being made Mark
started to jump everywhere the handset
and the telephone fell off the desk
there was a little voice coming out of
the handset saying why i can't hear you
anymore what's happening there what's
going on
so we we told Paul the good news
there was an operator with us you know
it was one of the computer rooms in at ESRIN
and
he was from Nepal so was viewing at that
time
and Mark was really happy Mark was
jumping everywhere we are making history
we are making history we are making
history and that operator
roberto lapis
i'm going to call my mother and help us
to tell her any kodi was like one in the
night i'm making history that was really
really funny
and we
actually then phoned the head of the
department olivia morelli i think it was
about midnight
we also phoned the head of the
establishment francis roshan
and they both came in
uh i don't know how many heads of
institutes would do this today but they
both came in
and we had a glass of prosecco each and
saw the fantastic results
they were all waiting with baited breath
you know wondering um you know this
what's the issue are we going to solve
this so just being able to pass the
message on that the satellite worked
the instrument was working
perfectly
was you know being the bearer of of good
news and i still remember saying
olivia we better phone the project guys
in Kiruna and tell them you know we know
what it is and he said no
wait
until the morning i'll phone my director
tell him that we sold the problem then
we'll phone the project
[Music]
the first image was Flevoland and
actually the problem that Paul had the
genius to understand was there was a
simple
and stupid
misdefinition
of the signal components they're called
i and q
and the telemetry definition was the
inverse of the definition in the
processor so switching that everything
worked perfectly that was a trick it was
something really
very basic but no one were
confronted to that problem of the inq
inversion and by the way with
follow-on satellite we had problems like
that even with Envisat but we knew the
trick so immediately we do that and then
it worked but at that time we had no
clue
satellite was functioning perfectly the
SAR was functioning perfectly and i can
tell you
there were a lot of reliefed people
because
i don't think this was the first
satellite 500 million euros
and if it really was
uh kapot i don't think we would have had
ERS-2 or Envisat all the Sentinels flying
today
and you know looking back now
that moment was the start
of all of these you know amazing use and
application of of SAR not just with the
ERS-1 ERS-2 Envisat Sentinel but also
with RADARSAT and with satellites that
have been developed afterwards they've
learned so much from that whole so that
was um
an absolutely seminal and
thrilling moment to be
in the midst of all of that yeah they
were really concerned that the satellite
might not work and they could have been
obviously frieza
a big failure
which may have prevented us to do then
the following generation Envisat and
probably which would have prevent us
even to go the step forward with the
Sentinel and Copernicus program
so that reality that
ERS-1
first image
and the i would say the long city they
had for 48 hours then was removed and
then we have seen
30 years of progress in association at
ESA
with industry with our member state
but the the start of all beyond
Meteosat for meteo the start of all
was ERS-1 in particular that those
first SAR images
and after that of course everything
was was just fantastic we had
the pleasure and the privilege of
working with the world scientists on the
first
c-band SAR imagery and developing all of
the applications from scratch
and that's where i had some fun a few
months later in the field of SAR
interferometry you know my memory of
that is just
how lucky we were
to be able to
use those tools work with those people
and benefit from the expertise i
remember more or less i didn't sleep for
48 hours in the story but still this is
probably my best professional experience
and it was very early my career so an
incredible souvenir for me there was
information in
on agriculture on forestry
on oceans on ocean waves on ice you
could just select all of these images
and put them and people you could see
the science community just
raring to go
and and work on it and the rest is
history is as they say
now it's all routine and commonplace but
in those days it was trailblazing and a
privilege to be working with those
people
today we there's been a long discussion
about the archive data preserving the
archives
well
some of the observations the planet has
changed in 30 years
sea level has gone up temperatures have
gone up
there has been deforestation there has
been urbanization there has been coastal
change there have been glaciers
retreating
that data has contributed to our
understanding of all of that but it's
vital it contains the record of how the
planet was
so uh i mean everyone who contributed to
that was laying down
a historical record whose value today is
you know enormous
[Music]
the one thing i learned from all of that
is
that people who are in the space
business
problems are normal you know you're not
to be surprised that things don't work
and you sort of
get organized to understand and solve
the problems and i think that was the my
first real exposure
to how that worked and as i was saying i
i think we were dead lucky to have the
opportunity to just to be in a place to
do something about it but you know the
thing is i you know we're sitting here
discussing it and i i i think
we were just a tiny part
of you know an amazing team
of people you know and we we were just
happened to be there
uh and we had i mean it was the
foresight of uh actually
uh LiveEO and the ESTEC team to develop
this processor because if i think if we
had not produced the image there it
would probably come about
within the next 20 hours or so because
the guys up in in
in Kiruna were doing it and and i also
realized Paul was actually you know in
he was getting the information on both
sides so he was uniquely pleased to be
able to win and solve it but i just
think of the people you know one thing
is that moment but actually
you think of the amazing
experts
and and people we were able to work with
and without us having had the
opportunity to work with them
you know we wouldn't have had that
experience and it's really that team of
people you know who made all of that
happen and i think for us looking back
now uh more than just the moment you
know of that the joy of that is just
thinking what it took
to bring it to all of that all of the
skills and i think there's 80 companies
around Europe who built different
components all of those experts
instrument experts up in ESTEC that we
were working with you know you could
benefit from all of their expertise
and i think that's the essence of ESA
i remember in march we did the
first experiment to
say you could do differential
interferometers so you can measure
millimetric motion from space with with
those crazy corner reflectors nailed
across Germany thing about all that is
we were in the middle i mean it wasn't
us who did it we were in the middle of
an organization that had teams of
industry
teams of scientists the best scientists
in all the eastern member states and
beyond who we're all working together
and you could ask them would you do this
would you do that
and it just clicked into place and
produced these miraculous results first
results and that was just i think that
was like the learning experience from
ERS is this is how you operate a
mission you get up to achieve what the
mission is can achieve and then and
that's what's been done with Envisat
with the explorers you always
understand and from that you know learn
how to do more i think that's what the
success really is it's about you know
going beyond what you're initially
developing developing the science which
allowed to develop the application which
developed the user interest
and
and then we do even better satellite
more
more accurate more diversified and
area now we are 30 years of archive
where we see the indisputable fact that
the change are fast especially in the in
the polar areas
and that's also a sense of achievement
because you see what we have
contribute to uh to develop the usage of
first observation has been fundamental
really to open the eyes that it was
truly a climate change on gooey not only
with the temperature immediate ground
with whatever
occurence in particular polar areas it
was all satellites
we will know much less indeed now but uh
the satellite role is is fundamental in
the awareness
of uh uh climatic change uh and not a
climatic change you know like we had in
the past but the very fast the speed at
which it happens yeah you know
we've been part of you know delivering
all this information about what's
actually happening on the planet it's
been immense progress to know what's
going on
um
would be great if there was a similar
progress on people actually
taking action based on the information i
mean
huge uh insights and scientific
knowledge about what's changing on the
planet policies remember when we were
doing all that work in the in the 90s
governments were writing you know the
the framework conventional climate was
set up
though there wasn't an established
scientific opinion that said
conclusively that climate change was
linked to
human impact that came
uh in the late 90s early 2000s
uh so we were working with science
community who had for more than two
decades had been busy putting the
observation systems together when that
came through but uh i i think we still
have a long long way to go before you'll
see people uh
who you know really seriously take the
decisions based on the evidence
[Music]
i mean how you
sometimes ask is that an invented memory
or did it really happen
[Music]